Another huge shout out to Starlink. How
good do I sound right now?
>> It's flawless.
>> Shocking.
>> Nick, show this behind the scenes shot
of what it took to get us going.
>> Starlink is bananas.
>> That's amazing.
>> Do you guys want to know something about
the Starlink network that I think is
just kind of coming out now? Basically,
the Starlink network because it's
putting out radio waves and it can pick
up radio waves and you've got so many of
them. You've basically got a phased
array telescope looking down on the
Earth
>> and you can pick up what would otherwise
be stealth aircraft from above.
>> So this is a UFO detector. You're saying
>> it's a stealth airplane detector. It
basically Starink it could be a UFO
detector, but the Starlink network
basically becomes this incredible radar
system that sits above the Earth to look
down on things that would normally be
stealth from the surface of the Earth.
>> So does this mean we don't have to do a
science corner today? because you just
did it.
>> Jack,
>> great to see you. So, as one of the
architects of Bretonwoods 2.0, Sax is on
a high. He's coming in hot.
>> Let your winners ride.
>> Rainman David,
>> we open sourced it to the fans and
they've just gone crazy with it.
>> All right, everybody. Welcome back to
this week in AI. Sorry. Uh all-in
podcast and we've got a ton of news to
get to on the such an idiot. You're an
idiot.
>> I mean, it's just the every week is AI
on top of AI on top of AI.
>> You have a show called This Week in AI
and you cover nothing about AI.
>> No, no, we cover AI, but thank you for
the club. This week in AI.AI. Sign up
for the newslet.
>> This week in super intelligence.
>> I'm going to change the name. This week
in
chat DJ.
>> What I should say is we have four super
intelligences here. for super
intelligence is here to super
intelligence the week's news
>> to intelligently discuss
>> the news. Yes. And uh what a week it
was. Uh we were sitting here just a
couple of weeks ago or sitting in Los
Angeles I should say and there was a bit
of a chaotic moment. Hey, should we be
should we be auditing or deselling with
all this AI? And 3 weeks later,
President Trump held a super intelligent
summit in DC. Many of uh the besties
were there and uh or three or four I
should say. On Tuesday, President Trump
convened the biggest names in AI, Elon,
Jensen, Zuck, Daario, Sundar, Satia,
yada yada yada, all the way down the
line and everybody from the government
as well. I could ramble on about this,
but Saxs, I have I have a feeling you
were instrumental in setting this up.
So, maybe I'll just hand it off to you.
Tell us how this went down so quickly
and then what the outcome is of this
super intelligence summit.
>> Well, the reason it happened so quickly
is because President Trump convened all
of these people to the White House and I
think he's the only person who could get
all these CEOs of all these companies in
one room. I mean these are the leading
companies in the world across data
centers across chips, hyperscalers and
then obviously frontier models and many
of them frankly don't like each other.
They have disputes with one another. We
all know this. They may have lawsuits
with one another. All of that didn't
matter because President Trump called
them to the White House for this
conversation. And I've called it the
Bretonwoods of super intelligence. This
was the first gathering of really all
the critical players across the entire
stack of the industry and I think we had
a really good open and honest
conversation about both the
opportunities and the risks of super
intelligence and as a result of that
meeting I'd say during the meeting we
worked out this agreement that has come
to be known as the white house accord on
super intelligence that was then signed
by the six major frontier model
companies
And I think we'll now apply a new rigor,
a new set of controls on the development
of super intelligence so that the public
can be more confident that this will be
done safely. And if I could just
highlight a few of the the key features.
So first of all, the companies who are
developing these products acknowledge
that they are responsible. They have to
be the responsible actors. Let's not
deflect it onto to someone else or
anthropomorphize the models or talk
about the United Nations. These
companies accept responsibility. Number
one. Number two, they agree to have
internal controls and to have those
internal controls verified by an
internal team that does that. But we
don't just leave it to quote unquote
self-p policing. It starts there. But
then you have external auditors who will
then validate and verify that the
internal controls are working. And these
companies will set up an independent
committee of the board to then receive
those reports. And as Gavin Baker
pointed out this morning, you know, when
the board receives a report from an
external auditor, you can't disregard
that. It's not optional. The board has a
massive fiduciary duty to then act on
that. Otherwise, their DNO policy can
get cancelled. Right? So now the board
is going to receive the report of the
external order and they have to make
sure as a board that they're overseeing,
they're providing oversight to make sure
that the frontier development is
happening safely. And then finally,
sitting behind all of that, you still
have the FTC and the SEC, which have the
ability and the responsibility to
enforce the public commitments of these
companies. So although this agreement
was entered into voluntarily, the
governance that follows from it is not
voluntary. It is now day.
>> It's fiduciary. This is a critical point
because it's an audit because and D and
O for people who maybe not familiar with
the directors and officers that's the
liability insurance that that board of
directors has in case something goes
wrong. So this is got teeth to it even
though it was voluntary. It has a deep
deep hooks into the board of directors.
>> That's right. And and just one final
point on this is that again this White
House accord on super intelligence it
was convened by the president. It was as
a result of that discussion and that
conversation, we got the major companies
to sign it and I think everyone in the
room there's basically a consensus
around it and these controls can now be
implemented basically immediately or
very very quickly and it doesn't require
new legislation. It certainly doesn't
require some new international agreement
that's never going to happen. So this is
something that can be done right away. I
think it's a credit to the president and
I think this should in large part I
think address many of the concerns that
the public has about the safe
development of super intelligence.
>> Absolutely. And
>> and I think there's a lot of Democrats
right now who don't want to give the
president credit around this because
they want to keep using it as a campaign
issue, but the reality is that I think
the president dealt with it swiftly and
sensibly and practically. This is way
more practical than trying to declare a
pause on frontier development that China
would never go along with or creating
some DMV for models that again would
slow us down to the point where China
just wins. So this is very practical and
it's immediate and the president
deserves credit even though the
Democrats won't give it to him. But I'll
notice that even Jacob Coxin where you
know in a way you could say that
>> the whistleblower quote unquote
quit after 6 weeks who is working with
the PR firm for the
>> Yes. Yes. Yeah. So I would say fake
whistleblower because he was working
with the PR firm the whole time even
though he said he wasn't
>> artificial whistleblower
>> but the artificial whistleblower. But
look even he said that he was happy to
read this. He was giving credit to the
president. So maybe everybody else
should as well.
>> Even the most cynical person Shimoth
looking at this would say great first
step right like if you just wanted the
global UN United Nations of AI this
would be a great precursor to that. a
first step where everybody's opting in
to be regulated to regulate themselves
as we discussed on this very podcast
with the MPAA analogy and here we are
three weeks later. Take us behind the
scenes. There was one notable addition
to the group of AI executives. Daario
from Anthropic is obviously very
anti-Trump. He has never shown up for
these things. The organization is 96%
anti-Trump, left-leaning, etc. But he
participated. So, how did Daario wind up
participating in this? How did he wind
up doing dinner one-on-one with the
president? Take us to the palace
intrigue here. Daario was a
conscientious objector. He did not want
to participate in any of this and now he
was front and center. I can tell you
what I heard and I just think it speaks
to how conscientious and gracious the
president is. I think there was like a
couple of previous events he noticed
that Daario wasn't invited and actually
just called and said you know this was
an oversight and invited him to dinner
and I think that's how it started and
they had dinner I think two nights
before that was widely reported
and then he stayed and he was at the
dinner so I think it was just
very smart strategic thing to do. It was
also a very conscientious and and very
polite thing to do as well just to make
sure that this is a broad coalition of
people that were included. And I think
that's that's sort of been the general
pattern that the president has
exhibited. Let me maybe give you a
couple of other
things that happened at the lunchon that
had an impact on me. The first was it
sounds like a very simple statement but
the gravity of it kind of has built in
my mind as I thought about it. He says
whoever wins super intelligence wins.
And then he just stopped talking. That
was the first line of his prepared
remarks. And then he said it again. And
when you think about it, he's completely
right. There is no world in which you're
going to have this multinational corpus
of people trying to allocate wins and
losses on this thing. This is on the
order of the industrial revolution. In
fact, Saxs had some really nice comments
at the lunchon which framed it as even
bigger than the industrial revolution.
He went through the numbers and it's
bigger than the industrial revolution
and like three or four other things all
added up together. This thing is still
bigger.
>> The railroads, the canals, and the
electrical grid combined
>> and the pyramids and the great wall to
it.
>> Well, that was in the Wall Street
Journal last week.
>> When you think about it that way, it's
very important that we win. And so he
started by setting the stage that way.
He had a couple of other specific things
which was it's really important that the
extremely positive use cases
that exist out of AI and now SI are
demonstrated and he said you have a
responsibility to lead with the benefits
and then he said you also have a
responsibility to impact the local
communities in which you operate and he
pointed at Meta as an example of a
company doing really good things with
teacher bonuses and hospitals and we
heard about that from Dena at the All-In
Summit.
and he said, "You need to continue to do
these things, but meanwhile, we have to
have the checks and balances to trust
and verify." After the lunchon, I had to
fly to Orlando because we at 8090 have a
long-term partnership with Ernston
Young. And I was speaking to their 3,400
partners. And one of the things that
Ernston Young and 8090 were doing was
building an entire audit infrastructure
for super intelligence. And what's so
cool is that we had been building it for
EY as our first customer, but on the
heels of this, I think we're going to be
able to take that infrastructure and
roll it out to everybody as Sax said,
because everybody's going to need it.
And there's really three things that
you're going to need in an age of super
intelligence so that boards are
protected, CEOs have visibility, and all
of the other compliance infrastructure
and governance infrastructure of a
company like DNO insurance and all these
other things are kept in place, which is
endto-end traceability, right? which is
to say when you deploy super
intelligence you need to know what's
going on. You need to map it to the
policies so that you understand what the
risks are. All companies have standard
operating procedures but you need to
know exactly when you're deploying super
intelligence how that builds on top of
your standard operating procedures. So
you need to map policies to risk and
then the third is you need to have
auditable evidence which is your way of
showing all of your downstream ecosystem
here's what I've done. So if anybody
taps you on the shoulder, whether it's a
lawyer, whether it's an auditor, whether
it's a regulator, whether it's in a
lawsuit, whether it's a customer, hey,
how did this happen? You can present
something. So these are like very
practical, sane things.
And you can expect folks like EY now to
deploy this broadly and quickly to all
of the companies that they work with.
And this is just one extra step. But if
you think about how fast this happened,
this is like 3 weeks
and you have this solution where the
alternative was hit the pause on
trillions of dollars of GDP so that we
could sort this out in a multinational
body. The alternative was crazy. So I
think what happened was historic and
important.
>> Was there any push back on the dumerism
narrative? Take us behind the scenes.
>> Jensen was really powerful. He said
something to the effect of alarmism
without solutions is unproductive
>> which I thought was helpful grounding
but he said alarmism with solutions is
helpful. Everybody had the same
perspective in the room to be honest.
>> Was that directed at Daario that
comment?
>> It was just generally said but I think
you know if we had to guess who was
>> did Dario respond after that? I mean,
you know, Susie and I were sitting right
across from him, so it was very fun just
to watch his reactions in general.
>> So, please unpack it. What was his
reaction to that comment?
>> I mean, like, he listened.
>> Got it. Who moderated the discussion,
Sachs? How was this moderate? Were you
the moderator? I noticed I didn't get an
invite. The world's greatest moderator
wasn't there, but Trump's a pretty good
moderator himself. Who moderates?
>> The president moderates it. The
president actually actively moderates.
>> Oh, yeah. No, no, no. He
>> Give an example of his moderation. I
would like to take some notes here.
>> Well, first first we got there, you
know, this is in the east room of the
White House, I believe, and through the
back of the East Room, you get to the
where this new corridor to the ballroom
is going to be. And so, we did a quick
tour out there and he showed us what
they're building and it's really
amazing. And I predict that
>> which is the new ballroom,
>> the new ballroom and the new east wing.
>> Did you have to wear Did you have to
wear hats and go into the construction
zone? You're on the first
>> Yeah, we walked we walked out there and
um I mean the cranes were out there
foundation.
>> They are making record progress. You
know, the thing is like seven stories.
So, the ballroom itself is two stories,
but it goes five stories down.
>> Oh, wow.
>> So, there's all sorts of stuff that
they're building there.
>> Alley, the No, no. For the military.
There's all sorts of
>> I know
>> there's like all sorts of vaults that
they want. But in any event, and he's
going to have it done in like a year
under budget and on schedule,
>> by the way, when it's done, I predict
>> that it'll be so nice that all future
presidents will really want to use it.
And it's things that the White House has
needed for a long time. They're going to
look back and say, "Why did they give
him such a hard time doing this?"
>> A distraction, too. By the way,
>> the fact that we had a builder in the
White House who just enjoys doing it.
It's so good at it. I mean, why why
wouldn't you take advantage of those
skills?
>> Allin annual uh dinner party there.
We'll have our all-in gala at the uh
>> Yeah. Anyway, it's going to be a big
upgrade. So anyway, he he took us on a
little tour of that and then he presided
over the conversation. First he gave
some remarks and he spoke to the whole
group and then he started calling on
people to give their opinion and um and
so he he always moderates uh these
things
>> and then the most challenging did you
have a challenging moment where you kind
of went at somebody a follow-up
question? Anything like that? Well, he
just he kind of asked people what they
think and has there's a follow-up. And
then we had a a breakout session of the
six frontier model companies in the
Roosevelt room, I believe. And that's
where we kind of hammered out the the
accord. Although,
>> when you're hammering out that accord,
are you literally there typing it in
Google Docs? And and who's responsible
for this typo? There was a typo in the
in the tweeted version that came
>> I don't want to say he was responsible
for that but but if that's if that's the
only thing people can find to object to
that's not that's not so bad.
>> Was Satia in Microsoft Word and he just
had he was typing too fast.
>> Yeah. I don't know. But um but basically
what happened is Zuck and Jensen talked
through some of the highle principles in
the main lunchon
>> and then Mike Johnson the speaker of the
house actually had a copy and he read
the whole thing and then we discussed it
and there was general agreement and
accord with it and then we did the
breakout session and there was some
words smithing not much though to be
honest and everyone was just good with
it. Now, we had I mean the White House
had a statement that had been circulated
to the groups in advance that it was a
couple of paragraphs, but frankly, this
other statement had more meat on the
bone. You know, the the original
statement had the statement of
responsibility and it had the creation
of a working group to discuss, you know,
safety issues on an ongoing basis and
share best practices. But the the new
part were the internal controls, the
external audits and the committee of the
board. And you I think it's been
publicly reported now. So not really
giving anything away that you know
Zuckerberg and then Jensen I think had
kind of come forward with that idea
>> and everyone was good with it.
>> Any notable moments where somebody was
like hey I need a comma here or I want
to put an end here. I want to add
something to this. Any notable edits?
>> I mean like I said I mean people were
generally good with it and um they read
it and everyone's like yeah you know
Elon
>> which part do you think has the most
teeth will be the most effective at
making things more secure? Which if
>> the external audits the external audits
who's going to do an external audit then
I guess is it is it going to be an
Ernston Young type thing price or
scoopers or KPMG or
>> in my view they should be professional
auditors not these NGOs that that's my
view
>> you're going to see EY in short order to
hear announce something
>> and Fredberg when you look at this in
terms of the speed and velocity it
happened and you're I guess on the
president's science and technology
council now maybe you could speak to you
know how quickly this is all occurring
and what the impact might be in terms of
America's competitiveness because you've
had concerns. Hey, maybe slowing down
here means China catches up. So maybe
you could talk a little bit to your
prediction if any of the alignment here
of all of the companies. Also of note,
just for the audience, people are like
Sam Waltman's not there. His partner
Greg was there. So Sam was doing I guess
the launch of some new products they
had, but OpenAI was obviously
represented. So maybe you could talk a
little bit about what you think impact
the impact this will have on maybe the
American public and their view of AI. I
mean, look, I think we are, we always
assumed in the sci-fi novels that we
would be in an era of having robot wars,
and I think we failed to recognize that
the software came first and we are
actually having the AI wars. And there's
a war that I think we're in the middle
of right now where there's kind of one
side that wants to centralize, control,
manage, regulate, whatever the term of
the day might be, the technology. And
there's another side that I think is
cognizant of the reality of the
technology, which is that it is
effectively ubiquitous. We talked about
this in the past due to open- source
openweight models proliferating
the fact that you can run models on
small local machines that you don't need
large clusters to do things and that
we're seeing model after model come out
now that are not under the jurisdiction
of some centralized system or agency.
Therefore, it becomes very hard and
practically impossible to actually
regulate the development of the
software. That's the truth. It is what
it is. You may not like it, but it is
what it is. And those two sides are
going to continue to fight. I think that
the risks will rise. And as that
happens, I'm going to make two
predictions to your question.
The first one is that I think we will
see a massive rise in defense systems.
There is no turning off the open- source
open weight models or shutting down all
the data centers or centralizing command
and control. There are 197 countries on
Earth. They each have sovereignty.
There's energy everywhere. They're all
connected to the internet. Data centers
will exist all over the world. So, the
attempt to try and centralize and manage
the control of the software, I think, is
a fool's errand. But I do think that
it's going to mandate because the risks
will rise an increased amount of
defense. And so I think you know
companies like PaloAlto Networks I think
the investment in this space um what I
heard in DC this week with some
Fortune50 CEOs are very worried about
cyber defense. That means they're going
to start to make this their number one
priority to address at the board level.
That means the budgets for cyber defense
are going to go through the roof. Now
let me ask you a question. when you have
to do cyber defense in an era of AI, are
you going to use old school software or
you going to use AI?
>> Obviously,
>> you're going to use AI. And because of
that, because cyber defense is going to
need to grow, the US is going to need to
provide competitive AI for cyber
defense.
It is a classic arms race scenario. And
so, the US cannot simply step back and
pause and turn off AI. It is already
everywhere in the world. Therefore, the
risks are rising. Therefore, we need to
increase our investment in AI to
maintain our cyber defense capabilities
both at the enterprise level and at the
government level and potentially even at
the civilian consumer level. So, I think
that the cyber defense necessity
actually mandates that we continue to
build out data centers to support it.
The second prediction I'll make is I
think 12 to 18 months from now we're
going to shift away from this
conversation about managing models,
regulating models, controlling models,
estimating models, scoring models, all
this sort of stuff that's going on
because like we mentioned last week,
every 11 days we're seeing new models
get published now. It is unbelievable.
And this week Google released their new
model that also seems to be more
performant than any other model. And
every couple days we're seeing a new one
come out.
So the model control systems are not
going to solve any problems. What I
think is going to end up happening, and
this is a prediction no one may like,
but I do think we're going to end up in
a world where governments are going to
regulate data center access and usage.
They're going to say the data centers
are here, but in order to maintain
defense capabilities, we are going to
decide who gets allocated a certain
number of GPUs, certain amount of
inference, a certain number of chips, a
certain number of servers. Because at
the end of the day, one of the key
metrics of cyber defense is going to be
how many machines do you have allocated
to defend your systems against how many
machines are coming after your systems.
And it is again a classic arms race
scenario assuming model convergence. And
even you know if models have slight
advantages over others, it seems to be
the case that we will maintain pacing.
And if we're maintaining pacing, then
the number of machines allocated to a
specific task is going to be a key
measure of how well it performs in that
task relative to another set of machines
doing the same task. You're just going
to need to allocate more machines to it.
So if you're going to allocate more
machines to it, you're going to end up
having the government say, "Wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait. We need the US
financial services system to get X% of
the GPUs in America. We need to make
sure that Y% go to defense. We need to
make sure that Z%
>> you're saying it's all going to get
nationalized and allocated top down.
>> I think that's where the regulators are
going to end up having to play a role.
You can kind of think about data centers
becoming the utility which is the clouds
the neoclouds effectively the government
will end up saying wait a second we're
not allocating enough to JP Morgan we're
not allocating enough to the financial
services system and ultimately the
number of machines that are being
>> market take care of that. Yeah, it's an
opportunity to sell into the government.
Now Google and Amazon Web Services,
Cruso, whoever can just sell more
servers and the government then can say,
"Hey, it is now Sachs
National Security that we build more
data centers and we're going to clear
the road for it based on that
inevitable."
>> Yeah. Here's the part that I
>> blocking a data center if we need it.
That would be like blocking tanks being
built during World War II, right? I
mean,
>> yeah. Here, here's the part I agree with
is it's not just about the capability of
the model. It's about how much compute
you have to run it. And we want to have
more compute than our adversaries. And
if we continue with this anti-data
center crusade, we're going to be at a
severe disadvantage. We already know
that the precursor for data centers is
power generation. And China's doubling
their grid every decade, and we've been
flat for about 25 years. That's a huge
problem. Now I went back and looked
throughout the course of the 20th
century. The United States was on a pace
to double its electrical grid every
decade. That's what we did. We actually
grew power generation enormously. And
those were in the days when America was
a great industrial empire and basically
dominated the world in manufacturing and
industry. We did not have a problem
doing this. We found ways to do it.
Obviously the power generation plants,
the power plants were being built
somewhere and they found places to put
them where they didn't encounter too
much nimbe opposition. They figured out
a way to do it. Think about that. Every
decade of the 20th century until
starting around the 1970s when it slowed
a bit. They were doubling the grid every
decade. '7s it started slowing but the
growth continued. And it wasn't until
the early 2000s that basically we
flatlined. Why is that? Because of
de-industrialization, globalization. We
shipped all those manufacturing jobs
overseas and then people went to work in
offices so we didn't need as much power.
Efficiency played a little bit of a part
in it as well. But we kind of lost that
muscle of how do we basically keep
doubling our power grid every decade. We
have to get that back. And um again
this, you know, anti- data center witch
hunt that I'm seeing going on, it's so
misguided. Look, data centers have been
around for a long time. Data centers
serve the internet. They serve all the
mobile applications on your phone. They
serve now AI. But they serve all the the
uses of computers that we use. And to
blame them for any specific application
just seems totally misguided. If you
have concerns about things like
surveillance or privacy, by all means
like strengthen the privacy laws, right?
I'm all in favor of that, but just
trying to ban
>> the data center seems insane. Sax, what
everybody wants to know, you have been
uh pretty critical of the Anthropic
Computer Corporation and specifically
Daario and the leadership there. He was
at the event. You guys met, I think
perhaps for the first time. Tell us
about Daario's participation there. And
did you guys talk a little bit about
your criticism of him specifically, of
the organization specifically, and all
of this dumerism and effective altruism
and all this, or did it not come up? No,
I mean, look, I think that Daria was a
good sport. It's true. That's the first
time I met him in person. I talked to
him on the phone before, but u look, he
was a good sport throughout the event.
Um, it was not adversarial or hostile.
Obviously, he has his own views and he
represented them, but fundamentally
everybody got on the same page and
signed this.
>> Did you shake hands with Daario?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. He joked. He said,
"Oh, my nemesis." You know, he sort of
joked.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yeah. So, that's kind of funny. Yeah.
>> Did you invite him on the pod? I forgot
to invite him on the pod, but he's
welcome.
>> You have his phone number and are you
going to invite him on the pod? The
world wants to know
>> if you want me to. But look, I think
it's good that he talked to the
president and had dinner with the
president. I think the president should
talk to all the major players in the
space. He should hear the full spectrum
of views and I trust the president's
going to, you know, arrive at the right
policy and solution. So, I think it's
good for him to hear Daario. I mean,
look, I think
>> any insight into what happened at that
dinner. What was President Trump's view
of Daario? He said he's an interesting
guy. There were some interesting quotes.
And he he dragged him from the back of
the group in the presser and threw him
out front. I saw you were right behind
him. Zuck was right behind him. You guys
had a little chuckle at the president
>> pushing him forward to
>> No, we weren't. We actually I forgot
exactly what No, no one was making fun
of Daria. Just implying that
conversations going on grabbed him from
the back and said, "You have to speak."
That I think that was kind of a a cute
moment. It was an affectionate I saw it
as an affectionate moment that he wanted
Daario to be part of the group and speak
on behalf of the group. I saw it as the
opposite. Yeah.
>> Yeah. He gave him a pat on the back. And
and look, I think
>> listen, Dario is a very special person.
I didn't, you know, fully appreciate it
till we're all in that room together.
There's obviously a wide spectrum of
views in that room. There's different
levels.
>> Spectrum is a good word. Spectrum.
>> There's there's an autism spectrum.
There's a there's a spectrum of autism
spectrum in that way.
>> You feel you felt very comfortable, Sax.
>> Well, I mean, you guys call me the
Rainman, but um I mean,
>> Rainman lighting is really functional.
>> I don't mean this as an insult, but you
know, Daria is sort of the Dustin
Hoffman in that room. And then Tom
Brown's like the Tom Cruz character
who's trying to like translate him. They
weren't wearing the same suit or
anything, but um
China, Russia, meet my mutants. Okay,
I'm forming like the X-Men here. Okay,
these are brainiacs. They're a little
bit weird on the margins, but they're
getting done for America.
>> Shimoth, you certainly uh must have had
an an interesting uh time there.
>> Tell us a little bit more of the the
palace intrigue. What was President
Trump's vibe? He seemed he was
incredibly engaged and excited. And I
just want to say, listen, you don't have
to be a fan of President Trump or a
Republican to appreciate what happened
here. and compare it to when Biden
excluded Elon from the EV summit. You
you need to as the president of the
United States be bipartisan and include
everybody in these things. We're all
part of the same team. It's called team
America. And I thought this was a great
juxtaposition of that. You had a lot of
people who were extremely critical of
the administration who were there to
make America stronger, to make America
win the AI race, the super intelligence
race. Most people have said this at this
point, so this is sort of beating a dead
horse, but he is a generational
political athlete. I mean, I don't think
we've seen anybody like him. And so,
he's extremely comfortable around all
kinds of people with all kinds of
differing views, and he's conscientious.
And so, when he notices things are not
right, he sets them right. He talks to
as many people. And I think you have to
be really impressed with that. like this
is a an incredible pattern that I hope
outlives him which is this idea that
when you have very complicated problems
when you use industry to be a sounding
board and then you sit with industry in
real time and then you craft these
accords in real time and when that
industry represents the entire political
spectrum as you said Jason some who are
with you and some who are against you
and some who are in the middle that is
the right way to govern in my opinion
because you have the best chance of
doing something that's sustainable and
that's realistic and that comes back to
this point that is getting lost which is
whoever wins super intelligence wins and
I think if we just keep that in mind
this is the pattern that hopefully
outlives
the president which is that whenever you
run into any other thorny issue and I
would say this to whoever is going to be
president 28 and beyond Democrat
Republican it doesn't matter get the
smartest people from that industry in a
room. Make sure that that's filled with
both people that support you as well as
may not necessarily support you and then
hash it out in the room and force a set
of realistic principles that everybody
can then build a business around. That
is very smart politics and governance. I
just wanted to go back to something you
said before because I was having this
conversation with Phil Deutsch. This is
about the data center thing.
He made this point to me which I think
is really important. When you look at
the impact that the Iran war had on the
price of oil, the most interesting
takeaway was actually how little
the price of oil moved
during all of these blockages in norm
because what really happened was there
was a lot of supply and generation
shifting that occurred. Right? we were
able to shape in real time Jason how to
generate energy and the real takeaway
from my perspective is that the
generation of electrons is actually the
critical thing not necessarily the
generation of energy as we've
classically thought about it now why
that's important is the data center now
becomes the critical symbol of national
security because the ability to generate
electrons and then the ability to make
sure that we can compute the resources
that we need to run our economy is going
to start from those things and so
domestic energy production I think also
is this hugely important thing that is
going to move from a domestic policy
issue to a national security issue and
that's why I think the data center thing
and and sort of why I I disagree with
Freeberg I understand where he's coming
from because this is why the data center
will get so much scrutiny but I also
think the opposite will happen which is
more the Sachs idea of the free market
because it is so critical similar to how
we responded after the Persian Gulf for
and how we responded after the gribble
war on terror. What do we do? We doubled
and tripled down on n gas and domestic
oil production. Similarly, I think the
domestic production of electrons becomes
so critical because the the data center
becomes this national security
infrastructure. That's so important.
>> Yeah. There was this great
video from years ago where Milton
Freriedman was at a law school and he
was asked a question by this kid about
when do we have a responsibility to act
to save someone's life and can the
government mandate that I do that and
doesn't that take away my freedom in a
free society? And the way the kid asked
it, Milton Friedman responded by saying,
"Hey, you started out talking about your
responsibility in society." And by the
end of it, you were telling me about
what government needs to do. And he's
like, I would argue that those two
things are not the same. And that the
point you should take note of is that
you don't need government to solve your
problems when society is giving you a
clear signal of what the right and wrong
thing is to do. that people collectively
can and will solve their problems, take
their actions, choose the right path, do
the right things, and businesses can and
will respond accordingly when the market
is telling them something. When society
is telling them something, they don't
need the government to be responsible
for executing the actions and taking
regulation onto its shoulders for them.
And I think we saw that this week with
Nvidia's launch and OpenAI was very
declarative about how they're being more
precautionary before they release
models. But this morning, Google also
launched Synth ID. And Synth ID is a
system for watermarking proteins that
are produced with AI. So the sequence,
the DNA sequence that codes for the
protein will actually now have a
watermark in it. And it's being broadly
adopted. And the protein itself, the
three-dimensional construct of the
protein will actually have an embedded
watermark in it as well. This is
actually a pretty amazing technology
that Google developed uh for creating
watermarking and defense systems in AI
bio. And I think we are starting to see
the market respond actively
to what society is saying and not need
these government people to come in and
take over and in the process put
everything at risk.
>> By the way, I saw that clip. It was
going viral as well. I thought it was
the young I don't know why I watched it.
Yeah,
>> he was a law school kid. The young guy
was articulate. Milton Friedman was
unbelievably articulate as always. But
Jal, what was what was your view? I'm
curious what's your view just seeing it
happen real time. What were you
thinking?
>> Yeah. Well, I was actually ironically
invited to come down to the White House
for the first time, my friend Joe Jebia,
who launched America.gov this week,
which was a spectacular launch. We're
making the American uh government as
efficient as private industry. He's the
co-founder of um
>> Airbnb,
>> co-founder of Airbnb and an incredible
design. He went to Risy with his uh
partners and so just shout out to him.
If you haven't seen America.gov, it's
stunning.
>> I spoke on a a panel with Brooke Rollins
and Sean Sankar at the event. It was an
incredible event. The whole cabinet
showed up. The president signed the
email and even guys like Andrew Rossin
gave this like standing monologue on why
it was so incredible for America to see
this. It was not partisan at all. It was
just upgrade America's technology
infrastructure for the citizens and it
was fantastic.
>> Yeah. And by the way, and sorry, Jacob,
I'm sorry to interrupt you, but I just
want to give a shout out to Joe because
>> he did that work with his own money.
People think that this was like some big
government investment. Joe,
>> I'm not aware of that. Wow.
>> Joe and others put up personal funds and
gave up their personal time despite
their success in their private careers
to step in and do this work for America.
And I just think it was an incredible
rally and cry for all of these
technologists to get together and build
something great together for America.
And it was a really beautiful day. It
was great to be there.
>> Just No, no, it's it's fine. From the
outside, it was incredible. Um, it's
just awesome to see the power of all
these uh American industry together. Not
a critique, but an end to add to it. Uh,
I think the next piece of this puzzle is
to start to include Americans in this
the bottom half of the K-shaped
recovery. Where's the teacher? Where
where's the teenager going into college
and all of this? Where's the, you know,
American tool belt worker, the plumber,
etc. You know, it looks from the
outside, I think, uh, from to a lot of
Americans that this is still a bit
scary. So, there's more work to do
there. I was on a flight on Delta and
the the flight attendants asked me what
I did and I was talking to them and they
said, "I'm so scared of this AI stuff.
I'm so glad I'm retiring because I I
don't want to lose my job, etc."
Americans are still petrified of this
technology. They still think they're
losing their jobs. They still think it's
dangerous. So, I thought this was like a
great first step, but there's more work
to do to pull Americans back off that
ledge. And we need to, and I think this
is where the president or the next
president could have a really major
impact, is to start forcing American
companies to not just thinking about how
they make more money, how they get more
green lights for their data centers, how
they get less regulation and more free
markets, but how does this impact
education? How does this lower the cost
of education? How does this build more
homes? How does this help? How did
people get more health care, you know,
at a lower price? That none of that was
addressed. That doesn't mean I'm I'm
giving any criticism of this event, but
that's the next piece. The next time
President Trump brings together this
many powerful people, they should talk
about the American public, not just the
data centers.
>> So, a couple things. He did ask for
people to do just that and actually
showcase some of these things. And he
was very specific. He did that and he
also said you need to show direct
positive impact in the local communities
in which you do business. He was very
direct. That was super blunt and one of
the first few things he said. Um I
wanted to build on your other
>> by the way that did not come across at
all. The the the real critique from the
public that I think is valid here is it
looks like we're just helping
that is something the billionaires and
the companies I don't mean to sound like
Bernie Sanders. They need to address
this themselves. It would be great if
they started saying like Facebook did
with the with the free tool belt stuff
and the training. We need to see more of
that. And I think housing, education,
healthcare is where Americans will start
to appreciate this.
>> I told you that right after
the White House lunchon, I flew to
Orlando because the
>> Erns Young has two day offsite for all
their partners. Okay, but listen to
this.
>> I'm not going to say this person's name,
but this person is a very well-known
Democratic person. They were on stage
and they have this whole riff about
doomerism and they're so cavalier about
it. They actually included the people in
the room as part of the claim that
they're all going to be out of jobs. And
I'm standing there backstage and I'm
like, "What are you talking about?"
>> It's not rooted in details. It's not
rooted in data. It's not rooted in fact.
This is a very well-known person, very
grounded theoretically in what the data
should show.
>> Shame and name. But what you realize,
well, I mean, I'll say it to you, but
maybe we bloop it up, but it's And I was
like, what the what is going on? And so,
to your point, Jason, it is very
partisan, and I said this last time on
the pot, there's an incredibly important
incentive for folks that are not in the
power structure today, i.e. Democrats
to take up the dumerism call to action
because it is a very straightforward way
to whip up fear and to then catalyze
that to power in the midterms and then
in 28. So you're going to see
>> that's going to win you votes for sure.
Yeah.
>> No, when I went on stage the first thing
I did was I was like she's wrong and
that's not true. And in fact everything
tells us all the data up until now that
there will be more jobs and more to do.
And I said the people in this room will
be making more money in the next four
years and 5 years than less money. There
will be more work to be done, more
judgment, more taste to be imposed. And
so I have a real issue with this
narrative because I think it's just
fundamentally wrong. And it does not
come from a place of datadriven fact. It
comes from a decision that the political
calculus is the doomerism is a way to
fment
distrust and displeasure and then to use
that at the polls. And I understand that
as a political tactic, but I think it's
important to call it up. This is why I
say we're in the AI wars. I mean, this
is the actual war. There won't be a
robot war. It's this battle right now
about who's actually going to have the
technology and the progress and who's
not.
>> Well, who's going to benefit from
Freeberg? who's going to benefit from
it, right? Rich people or poor people,
middle class. People don't know what
open source is. No one knows what an
open weight model means. No one
understands any of this stuff. And
they're looking at the rich guys at the
White House. And I agree with you, Jal.
I think the public perception and the
public narrative on this thing is I
don't get it. I see a bunch of wealthy
people kind of hanging out with the
president at lunch making a bunch of
decisions that I don't have a voice
around. I don't even know what's going
on. I don't even know what they're
doing. And then I turn on the news. I
turn on the TV, I look at my Instagram,
and everything's about the end of
tomorrow. And so I'm all about shutting
it down. No problem. This is why I think
it's important to have the conversation
that we're having about why does open
source and openweight AI benefit
everyone because there's no company
that's charging you a toll for this
digital technology. It's just like the
internet. We maintained an open
internet. There was a huge fight. People
forget the fight that we had for the
internet. When the internet was first
starting out, there were all these
efforts to privatize the internet, to
create gatekeepers. There were these
efforts by all the telos that they were
going to be the gatekeeper to the
internet and charge you different
amounts of money to access different
websites. You weren't going to a be able
to just go to Yahoo or AOL if you didn't
pay a fee to your telco to be allowed to
access Yahoo or AOL. And we made it
illegal and we made it an open internet.
And I think the same is happening right
now with AI. People don't see the fight,
the war that's going on, but there is a
contingent of people that, to Chimath's
point, recognize the political value of
regulatory control and capture, and they
are fighting to create gates and to
create systems of control and ultimately
new power.
like you solve the whole fighting we are
fighting the other side is actually
fighting for openness with AI
>> and it's well organized like it I'm like
when you go to these places and you
realize that these extremely successful
people are being deployed with very
tightly scripted talking points that all
point to dumerism you realize that this
is like extremely designed
and then you know the rest of us who are
working in this arena and actually can
see that there are more positive
benefits it's a negative and that there
are more people making more money than
before up and down the income spectrum.
We are not as organized as they are.
That's what I will say for sure. And I
think that the positive message of super
intelligence and the economic upside is
not nearly as well trafficked as the
downside doomer message because that
goes from top to bottom in an extremely
organized repetitive way. And that's why
Jason the flight attendant has the
talking point. So they are winning.
>> And by the way, the talking point was
given to them by Daario. The talking
point was given to them by Elon when he
said, you're not going to need to have a
job. Those talking points were handed
out. Now they're being reversed. Still
work to be done. I think next time, best
piece of advice, save three seats,
Sachs. Bring a Salon. Bring somebody
representing like teachers. Bring
somebody representing health care. Bring
somebody thoughtful non business person
who could represent other constituents
in this. save a seat at the table for
people who, you know, the every man and
woman of America can relate to who says,
"Hey, yeah, this maybe this will help my
kid, you know, when I get a personal
tutor for them." Like Salon would be the
perfect example of Khan Academy. Sax,
you got any final thoughts here?
>> Well, I mean, I kind I kind of wanted to
broaden out this conversation to the
economy as a whole because I do think
that the dumerism is affecting people's
perception of the economy.
>> Yeah, that's why I'm bringing it up.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And I think that actually there's
been a tremendous amount of economic
data in just the last week or two
showing that the economy is much
stronger than people are giving it
credit for. I mean, yes, I know that
diesel prices are too high and rates are
high, but those are the only two
variables that you ever hear about.
Let's look at some of the other numbers
that have just come out because I think
it's pretty extraordinary. So, first of
all, Q2 GDP was revised up to 2.2% 2%
up from 1.5%. So that's basically 50%
increase. Economists had expected no
revision. Q1 was also revised up to 2.5%
from 2.1%. And if you look at the Q3
growth, it's tracking well above that.
The Atlanta Fed GDP now is showing
around 3.7% as of late last week. August
payrolls just came out plus 162,000. The
consensus was only 55,000. which is a
beat of about 107,000 jobs. June and
July were also revised up by combined
55,000. So unemployment is still near
record lows at 4.1% even though labor
participation rose.2%
to 61.6%. So good news on the jobs
front, good news on the GDP front. The
economy is running hot. And then there
was also some good news on inflation.
We saw that core PCE just came in at
3.0% 0% versus 3.3% expected. So
inflation is still a bit too high, but
actually it is cooling and beating
expectations. And then finally, you look
at manufacturing. We're seeing a huge
wave of re-industrialization in this
country. A couple of the measures are
the Chicago PMI and then ISM
manufacturing. They both are well into
expansion territory and beating
forecasts. Just one last point, let's
talk about poverty for a second because
I want to address the idea that this is
just a K-shaped recovery. So, if you
look at US household income is now at
record high. The median household income
in 2025 is almost $90,000.
And after tax household income is
growing again in the second Trump term.
It's averaged 3.1% a year in Trump 47.
It was 3.9% in Trump 45 and it was minus
1.2% in Biden's term as a 4-year
average. So we're seeing that after tax
household incomes have risen by 3.1%
just in 2025. And the poverty rate in
the US has fallen to its lowest level in
history, 10.2%. So, you know, the
poverty rate, the child poverty rate,
these are all at historic lows. The
average households um real income after
inflation, after taxes is increasing for
the first time in years. So, there is a
lot of strong economic data out there.
And I I think that this is why if you
know if I was to guess, I actually think
that the Republicans are going to do
better in the midterms than some of
these polls are predicting because I
think the press around the economy has
been very negative. But I think people
are starting to feel that the economy is
accelerating. And that was actually a
headline in the Wall Street Journal just
the last couple of days that the economy
is accelerating right now. So again,
you've got this AI boom or SI boom.
You've got the the infrastructure
buildout that again the Wall Street
Journal said is bigger than the
railroads, the canals, and uh the
electric grid combined. And all these
things are basically fueling strong
growth in the economy. And again, I
would just dispute the K-shaped
narrative because the poor are
benefiting and the average household are
benefiting as well.
>> They don't feel that way, but uh I guess
you
>> I get that the sentiment I I agree with
you. The sentiment has not caught up
with the economic reality, but I think
it will.
>> We've got a a rate problem in the last
30 days or so, right? We've seen
short-term rates on treasuries climb by
60 basis points. That's a pretty
consequential climb. I think we haven't
seen a short-term yield this high since
going back to 2002. And so this massive
increase in rates is obviously going to
impact people's ability to refinance
their home, buy a new car, purchase
things on credit, and that's the
majority of Americans fall under that
umbrella. And I think there's also kind
of an economic challenge ahead with the
rate problem. And I I would argue, as I
always do, that the rate problem is
fundamentally rooted in the federal
government and the insane spending.
And if you look at the impact that this
rate is going to have on banks, I worked
with Chat GPT, my my trusted analyst, my
financial analyst in my office here to
help kind of figure out what's the
impact of these rates actually going to
be on banks and what the impairment
would be. There's 4,295
banks that have positive equity that
report FTIC their balance sheets every
month. Based on the actual reported
balance sheet of these banks,
about 95 banks are going to see an
impairment of more than 20% of their
equity in the last 30 days or so. And
those reports start to come out on
October 30th. So, the thing I worry a
lot about is on October 30th, we're
going to kind of see all these financial
reports coming out from all the banks,
all the lending institutions, and
there's about 95 of them that are going
to say, "Hey, we've got more than 20%
impairment charge on our equity." That's
going to be a massive kind of shock. And
then what are the implications of that?
And that's where we're going to start to
wake up to the fact that the rate
problem isn't just a purchasing problem
for consumers, but it may actually have
a bit of a rippling effect here in the
economy starting with the financial
institutions. So they publish their next
monthly reports on the September 30th
ending period on October 30th. And
unfortunately, it coincides right with
the election cycle. So there's going to
be all this noise about, hey, how bad
are things looking while we're trying to
go through this election. So Sax, I
don't know like you know if there's any
view on how we fix this rate problem,
but it's pretty nasty and it's gonna
have to I I conceded it up front that we
have two issues in the economy that are
negative. We have diesel prices and
rates. But then I went on to lay out the
case for why there's so much other
positive economic news that's not really
being covered. Look, if you compare
rates to the nominal growth rate of the
economy, and those two things are highly
correlated over time, you can see the
economy is running really hot right now.
And that is part of the reason why rates
are going up is because you have to
compensate people for a a real return.
And you know, you've got inflation in
the threes and then you've got GDP
growth at 3.7%.
Then rates are going to be high as well.
Look, I think this all comes back to
price of diesel because that obviously
has a lot to do with not just people's
price at the pump, but also diesel is an
industrial input and the transportation
costs get baked into all these goods. I
think if we can just solve that problem,
then gas prices come down, inflation
comes down, we can get rate cuts on that
basis. So I think that's the last piece
here. I think the economy is already
doing again very well, 2.5% in Q2, 3.7
in Q3, but if we just get that last
piece, I'm not saying there's not a
little bit of work to do there, I think
the economy will take off like a rocket.
>> Yeah, I think the conditions are right.
You're right. I think the federal
spending problem is still persisting,
though. It's almost like pouring acid on
everything. Like you've got all this
great stuff growing and then you just
have all this federal spending which as
you and I both know is like negative
productivity spending and it's uh
creating fake employment and it's doing
all sorts of bad things. But man, if we
don't get spending, you know, as Scott
Besson has talked about to 3% deficit as
a percent of GDP, these rates are only
going to get worse and that could
basically just shoot us in the foot.
>> You know, we we all agree about spending
as a as a long-term problem and and it's
a bipartisan problem. and we have to fix
it. I would just say that look, I would
say about 6 months ago, people said that
if we get a spike in gas prices, we're
going to have 1970s style stackflation.
That has not happened. Instead, we're
seeing a super hot economy. And yet, gas
prices are a little high. But, by the
way, during the Obama presidency, we had
over 300 days of Brent crude over $100 a
barrel. So people forget that we've had
the economy do well over large stretches
of time with gas prices at these levels.
It's just the diesel prices are a little
bit high and that has to do with
refineries. Frankly, it'd be good if
Zolinsky stopped hitting Russian
refineries. That hasn't helped the the
problem. But look, so we just have that
one that one issue and I think we can
resolve it. There was a report this
week, I think it was in the Guardian,
which is not a proTrump publication,
saying that more oil got out of Hormuz
this week than since the beginning of
the war. So, I think we need to kind of
wrap up that issue. Gas prices come down
and then I think that means inflation
will come down. It's already coming down
more than expected, but then we can get
a rate cut. I think actually right now
no one's pricing in the potential for
rate cuts here. It's all rate increases.
So, you know, if we could get some
relief there, get rate cuts, I mean,
again, the economy is going to rocket
even more.
>> We have two
tricky auctions that are coming up
and I think Treasury will be able to
navigate those well, just because I
think Scott has such a good handle on
how to do this and frankly how to do the
job. But once we get past those two
auctions, I'm leaning more in the Sax
camp. I kind of tend to agree with you.
There's going to be some growing
evidence about what to do based on what
happens from Europe as well. I don't
know if you guys have been tracking
this, but France is going through a
really complicated budget negotiation
right now. And they're about to shrink
the budget by probably 5075 billion,
which you can imagine in France that's
like ground zero for it's a oneway
ratchet to GDP going through the roof.
And so when the French start to make
guts and it's what Freeberg has been
saying, it's why were they forced to
capitulate? because of long rates. So
that's happened. Andy Burnham, who you
know bumbled his way into the prime
ministership of the UK, presented his
policy platform yesterday for an hour.
It's truly insane what he's saying.
This is an extremely muscular form of
socialism that he intends to impose on
the United Kingdom
and then to reemerge back into Europe.
And so he's going to try to undo Brexit.
He's going to try to double and triple
the size of government.
Not a mention of growth. Like how do you
grow the private economy?
Insane. So what you're going to see from
both of those two places over the next
year is I think going to tell us what
we're going to have to do in the United
States. But I tend to think that we're
going to see a little bit more growth
than that is expected. I tend to think
we're going to probably see a little bit
more revision. And I think that people
are sleeping on the fact that we are not
nearly as dependent on oil the way that
we used to be. And so even though we
used to breathlessly look at Brent crude
and WTI and all this stuff, I don't
think it matters nearly as much as it
used to. And I think that's crazy
because like the paradigm of rates and
the paradigm of currencies and the petro
dollar, all these intermingled things
that used to drive the global economy
are now getting rewired in ways that I
don't think anybody fully understands.
And that's very good for the United
States. So I think we have like the one
problem is we we do have gas prices at
the pump are up 50% since the Iran war
started
>> and that hurts the everyday consumer
significantly. It may not drive the the
GDP numbers down super aggressively
because of the industrial but the the
actual cost of living for the average
person.
>> But can I can I say something?
>> Yeah.
>> I I've looked at those numbers the
prices and they're terrible and I feel
bad for people that have to bear that
cost. But I think it's also important to
say that is not an input issue. That is
a refining issue. For decades and
decades, we turned off the refining
infrastructure that the United States
could have used. Okay? And so we now
need, as Sax said, the Russians, the
Chinese, we need as much refining
capacity as possible to take all of this
oil and to get it into usable forms. So
I hear you, but I think it's also
important to acknowledge where the
constraint is. The constraint is not the
oil.
>> Yeah.
>> The constraint is over decades and
decades of oil.
>> Let me jump in for a second. I hate to,
>> you know, put a a little rain on this
parade here, but uh two important charts
as we go into the midterms. Here is
Trump's Well, I and my core belief is
not enough has changed. And so the
American people, you pull up the first
chart, Nick. If we look at just since
Trump's been in office, I think the
challenge is nothing's changed. If you
look at unemployment, hasn't changed.
It's about the same. And then if you
look at inflation, it's still sustained
at that high 3s, sometimes dipping into
four, sometimes as low as 3.2, but never
into the twos. And GDP is, you know,
something that the American people just
don't feel. And if you look at this
chart, these are Trump's biggest
strengths. So, you have to ask yourself,
how did this administration go from an
incredibly positive feeling when Trump
2.0 came out to having just a net
negative on immigration, trade, the
economy, and inflation? And people's
perception is their own reality. And the
perception right now is that Trump and
this administration cares about foreign
wars and it cares about industry much
more than it cares about the average
American. And that is the exact opposite
of what Trump promised his own
constituents. And this what you see here
in these results is he's lost all those
independents he won with the promise of
Trump 2.0 and he's obviously never going
to win over uh Democrats and he's
starting to lose his base and the base,
you know, now fleeing and saying, "Hey,
you promised us you were going to deport
20 million people." Something I don't
agree with. But that didn't happen. So
now he's losing all those core
positions, the things that were supposed
to be a shrinks. And that's where you
have to wonder what is going on in this
administration that they just can't even
talk about the issues that the American
people care about. And obviously the war
just destroy this administration's
popularity with their own bait, with
their own base. They're going to get
shellacked in the midterms according to
all polls. And of course, Trump, if
anybody's going to pull a rabbit in the
hat, it will be Trump because he has
beaten the polls before, but this is not
looking good, gentlemen. And uh you
could spin sachs the last couple of
quarters, but
>> can I respond to this?
>> Absolutely. You can, by the way, this is
I wish it was different. I wish we had
2% inflation right now.
>> What is your prediction? What do you
think?
>> I would just look at I I just look at
poly market honestly and pull up the
poly market here. I think it's about 70
80% that the the Democrats sweep both.
By the way, over the next week, the four
of us are gonna have a squad on Poly
Market where we're going to make all of
our predictions, and then the audience
can kind of follow along and see how we
all do on our predictions, which will be
kind of interesting. But
>> I I don't Jamath, I I am not an expert
on polling, but I do think starting with
the the people actually betting money
and 63% chance the Democrats take the
Senate, 93% they take the House, and if
you put those together, there's a chance
they sweep both. You know, who knows?
With these polls, I do think I would
look at poly market first and if you
could zoom in there. The chances they
take both is at what now? Sweep 64% that
they sweep. So,
>> okay, let me tell you what I think is
wrong with this analysis.
>> Okay, go ahead.
>> So, okay, look. So, so I look I made
this mistake in 2022. Like I was sure
there was going to be a red wave in
2022. This is when Biden was president
and this was his midterms. Okay. Now,
and it ended up being like a red
trickle. I mean it was very
disappointing to Republicans that you
know they made gains but it was not a
shellacking. So what was the mistake
that I made? It was that I was only
looking at perception and I wasn't
looking enough at reality and I wasn't
balancing the reality. So for example
Biden's polling was in the 30s. He was
very low back then and inflation was 9%.
But if you looked at GDP growth and
unemployment those numbers were actually
pretty strong. So you know there was a
lot of talking down the economy based on
one variable which was inflation and it
was too high and it was a problem but
there were other variables that were
actually quite good. So the reality that
people were feeling wasn't as bad as you
know this like super hyperbolic view
that again all the pollsters have an
incentive to kind of exaggerate the
stuff and all the political operatives
always freak out. It's good for ratings,
>> but yes, it's good for ratings, but the
reality is the American people, look,
they went red, don't get me wrong, but
it wasn't the massive wave that everyone
was expecting was more like a red
trickle. I think here I don't think
we're going to get a blue wave. I think
we might get like a blue spritz. I mean,
listen, uh, I think that
>> listen, Biden wishes that back in 2022,
>> I'm saying that back in 2022, Biden
would have wished for the economy that
Trump has now. Okay? Yes, we have 3%
inflation. It's not 9% like Biden had.
Yes, gas prices are a little bit high,
but GDP growth is great. It's
accelerating. Unemployment's great.
Labor participation's great. Poverty,
the the poverty line
I think the Republicans are going to
surprise people
>> and keep the Senate.
>> And I think, you know, most people think
the Republicans lose the House. I guess
that's probably consensus, but it's not
going to be this gigantic wave. I think
it'll be
>> narrow if the Democrats win. And I think
it'll be a real headache for Hakeem Jeff
to keep all of these DSA Democrats in
line. If you remember when Kevin
McCarthy had the house, he had a very
thin majority and he lost his speakerhip
because he couldn't quite keep the
Freedom Caucus in line. I think Hakee
Jeff is going to have very similar
problems if the Democrats take the
House. So, look, I even noticed Mark
Halper's been predicting a blue tsunami
for the last month, but he's starting to
hedge that. So, I think the pro
Democrat, pro blue sentiment peaked, I
think about two weeks ago, and since
then it's been very positive economic
numbers for the president. The
Republicans need to go out there and
tell that story. You know, can't have
all this doomer stuff. We got to turn
this around. I think we just neutralized
this whole AI safety issue at the White
House. So, I think that the next month
actually,
>> if there war, what do you think the
situation would be?
>> Well, look, I mean, you know, again, I
said that the one missing piece here is
diesel prices. So, you get the price of
diesel down and that'll be the last
remaining unlock on inflation. That'll
bring rates down and the economy is
going to hit, you know, 5% GDP growth.
So without the war, do you think the the
Republicans could have swept
>> or there's ways of solving that problem
with diesel? I mean, and and look, in
the last week, I mean, this is the news
report, okay? You know, I don't know the
reality of what's happening in Hormuz,
but according to all the publications,
they just got a record amount of oil out
of Hormuz. So,
>> and they're doing night shipping with
the lights off kind of situation. Yeah.
Interesting. You have a prediction if we
can just wrap that. Look, I'm in favor
of wrapping it up, don't get me wrong,
but um I think the president has
indicated he'll do that. Uh he doesn't
want to be pressured into doing it
before the election.
>> You said that very clearly, what do you
think is going to happen here?
Prediction for the election. We're a
month out.
>> From the numbers that I'm looking at,
the Senate, I think, is very much a
tossup, but it I think can remain
Republican, and I think the Democrats
are going to have a slim majority in the
House.
>> Okay. Same as sex. Yeah.
And I think the the way that the
president can seal the deal, so to
speak, is I think you have to
focus on the economic gains and you have
to dispel
the doomer narrative. And I think if you
can stay focused on that for the next
month, I think the Republicans have a
pretty decent shot. Now, the other side
is also true. If you can distract people
and focus on the one or two things that
are still problematic like gas prices
and continue to reinforce the doomer
narrative, you have a chance to
overachieve if you're the Democrats. So,
I think this is how it's going to come
down. Jason, can you focus on a few
issues like gas prices or do you look at
a broad-based look at the economy that's
on one side and do you look at super
intelligence as a constructive force of
GDP growth or do you buy the boomer
narrative? And I think what we're going
to see is who is better organized and
who gets that message out the cleanest.
And whoever does that for sure wins the
house. Yeah. I think the dumerism
freeberg is like not a huge winning
issue. All I have to say is Trump
promised not to start a war. He did. He
promised to solve inflation. He didn't.
The end. And I think the Democrats
sweep. What's your take on what's going
to happen? Free.
You have any insights for Yeah, I think
the more important question is what
happens between
26 and 28.
>> Go ahead, take that one. That was my
followup.
>> I mean, I think
>> What do you think happens between 26 and
28? You know, whether we split, sweep,
either way.
>> Yeah, I I think that those are kind of
like a consequence and and it's not just
split or sweep. I think what happens
between 26 and 28 is
how far left do the Democrats go and how
much does that get hardened and then how
much do the Republicans splinter into
this kind of populist thing and do the
populists kind of fuse
and then we end up in this kind of
socialist takeover of America
>> the America first movement I think
you're referring to the Tucker call
>> I don't know I actually don't know if
that's even like you know remember there
was a tea party like there's a whole
bunch of manifestations of these social
emotions, these kind of public emotions,
they all kind of like fuse into
different words and different parties
and different groups. Who know who knows
where it goes? It's certainly unlikely
that the first manifestation is the one
that sticks and holds and becomes the
biggest one. I mean, look, I would argue
the Tea Party was sort of seated MAGA
years later.
>> Yes, of course. Yeah.
>> But this kind of populist movement does
not like if you look at the first
derivative of it, it's still positive.
like the populist sentiment is still
growing in America and that's what I
really care about the most because I do
think that that's where individual
liberties get destroyed as you know
populism effectively mandates a bigger
kind of government to solve our
individual problems
and I worry that we've got some looming
crises looming crisis number one being
social security looming crisis number
two being where rates are and the impact
that's going to have on affordability
looming crisis number three being that
this idea of an asset tax is actually
going to solve any problems where the
truth is like I've said in the past if
you took a 100% of the net wealth of all
the billionaires in the United States as
a tax a onetime tax and took a 100% of
their net worth it would fund one year
of the federal government all the
billionaires money combined is one year
of federal government spending it
doesn't really move the needle to do an
asset tax that there's a fundamental
restructuring of how we tax and how we
spend that's going to be necessary you
either need to tax the middle class
which is where 160 trillion of America's
$183 trillion net worth sits or you've
got to cut spending massively or you've
got to completely restructure these
entitlement programs. All of which are
deeply unpopular. All three of those
paths are deeply unpopular. So when
something deeply unpopular starts to
kind of be the only path, what happens?
And that's what I worry most about. And
I think that's all going to kind of come
to a head between 26 and 28. I I think
it's going to frame the political
calculus going into 28.
>> It's going to be fascinating and we'll
be here for it. I don't know if you guys
uh had time when you were busy here, but
there was a
hijacking that occurred slash terrorist
attack, I think, is the only way to
describe it. Fly Dubai flight from Dubai
to Tel Aviv. David had 174 passengers on
board. An Omani co-pilot apparently
stabbed the captain and tried to crash
the plane
in a 911 style attack.
passengers bravely uh subdued him and
there were off-duty pilots on the plane
miraculously. I mean, what are the
chances? And uh they somehow during this
terrorists trying to down the plane,
Freriededberg were able to not only
remove him, but get these offduty pilots
into the cockpit, level the plane, and
land it safely.
uh one of the most amazing acts of
bravery with this co-pilot who fought
off um the terrorist and then three or
four passengers were able to get into
that cockpit, drag the this terrorist
out and um yeah, land the plane. Your
thoughts, Freeird?
>> Well, I mean the eyewitness accounts
came out pretty fast and furious because
these guys had internet access as soon
as they were able to land in Saudi
Arabia and they started to provide their
reports. But what really I thought was
the most striking aspect of all of this,
despite the what I thought was
incredible heroism and bravery and just
a true kind of showing of human spirit
was how the media covered it. And I was
deeply saddened uh because I remember
9/11.
I remember the shock and the anger and
the stories coming out during that day.
I remember the media, the the the the
news channels were my source of truth
and I watched it all day. And then
yesterday this happened and and so here
here's an example. This is the New York
Times cover the day after 9/11. Hijacked
jets destroy Twin Towers and notice this
and hit Pentagon in day of terror. And
it really was a day of terror. It was a
truly tragic
event in human history. Regardless of
your political or social beliefs then or
now, the loss of life in this case, the
loss of life in conflicts that followed,
the loss of life in conflicts around
October 7th and that followed that is
all tragic and it's all terror and it's
all awful. And the reporting yesterday
on this event, which I found to be kind
of emotionally distressing, was almost
like a a strange casting of the
experience as being one of a fight
between two buddies that weren't getting
along
>> in the cockpit of a uh Yeah. got into a
scuffle of the original reporting. Yes.
>> The first one was New York Times came
out and said it was an altercation and
then the Journal called it a struggle.
The BBC called it a fight between
pilots. Sky News called it a brawl
between pilots. AFP called it, you know,
said they were fighting. Even CNN said
it was a altercation.
And there were direct eyewitness reports
coming out at this time about this guy
tried to take over the plane and crash
it. And this was clearly a terror event.
And we've stopped using this word terror
for some reason. Because when we use
terror, it doesn't allow us to
politicize and create sides of a story
and a long form narrative that I believe
so much of the media is trying to
portray. And I'm not going to try and
say what their narrative is and who's
trying to do it. But here's the next day
on the New York Times website.
So this is the day after when all the
facts of the case have come out. What
happened? This is the front page of the
New York Times today. a day after with
all of the witnesses, with all of the
journalism that would allow you to
validate multiply witnesses on what
happened on this flight that
investigators seek to establish a
motive.
The story is that the guy tried to crash
a plane full of passengers. He took over
the plane and he tried to do it. Number
one, bullet point 737 sustained the
enormous stress. Number two,
investigators seek to answer the motive.
And in bullet point number three,
Israeli politicians used the attack to
try to score points in this month's
election.
And so I just kind of lost faith
yesterday and today in how the media is
kind of characterizing facts on the
ground that there is human tragedy that
there is terror and that from their view
from their writing this ends up becoming
a place to kind of sell I think
unfortunately a narrative that is all
too popular and is what's going to sell
them and they don't want to lose people
by saying the wrong thing and they want
to say what they think is right and I
don't know who the individuals are
behind all of it but I just found it to
be pretty shocking. for me that 25 years
ago to today, how much has changed in
the landscape of the people that we
trust, that we call journalists to tell
us the truth of what's going on and to
try and reccharacterize such horrific
events because it doesn't quite conform
to a specific narrative that they've
been trying to sell for some time. So, I
was deeply upset about the whole thing
and I wanted to bring it up.
>> Yeah. I mean, reasonably upset.
>> Two different
>> and I do think a big sh big shout out to
the pilot.
>> Unbelievable. If you read the reports,
he wouldn't go to the bathroom because
he had suspicions that his co-pilot was
going to do something. He called for an
emergency urinary bag and he stayed in
the cockpit to pee in his urinary bag.
That's when the the guy tried to kill
him. He fought the guy off. He was while
he was stabbed and bleeding out to
death, heroically opened up the cockpit
door and screamed for passengers to come
and help. And then several heroic souls
stepped up and saved the day and saved
170 some odd lives. That's the story.
It's a story of terror. It's a story of
human heroism. I don't care where these
people are from. I don't care what
religion anyone is. I don't care what
political interest anyone might have.
This is the story that needs to be told.
And it is being kind of recast
by the media about Israeli politicians
trying to score points is what the New
York Times is trying to sell on their
cover page today. Yeah.
>> As opposed to the story of what really
took place here.
>> And then the New York Times, you know,
got so much over it that they
started Jake, you can cover this, but
>> Yeah. Yeah. in the New York Times
communications uh account says for based
on the the early tweet which was hey
there there was an altercation quote our
headlines and live coverage contain all
the facts were able to confirm as we
confirm them unlike activists and
partisans we don't publish speculation
or unverified information here's a gift
link to follow along to our reporting
yada yada so I guess two topics there
Sachs you have the real time issue which
is certainly very different than 911
And that was a an attack where people
took credit pretty quickly if I if my
memory serves me correctly. And in this
case, we're left to wonder lonewolf
coordinated attack, etc. But certainly
strange the next day's coverage, I think
at a minimum that they can't call this a
terrorist attack. A little bit odd. Your
thoughts next?
>> Well, I think we can probably infer what
the motive here was. I mean, it was
terrorism. Uh it this was a a Dubai
airline, but I think all the passengers
were Israeli.
>> Yeah.
>> One of the detail I thought was
interesting was that when the pilot
yelled for help, I guess
a few of the pastors stormed the
cockpit, the the terrorist was yanked
out of there by an Israeli plumber.
>> I love it.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't think that's like CIA plumber. I
think that was I think it's like a real
plumber.
>> Yeah, this guy has
>> those those Israelis are tough. I got to
say they're they're quite tough.
>> The bravery to jump in the cockpit like
that and then I just I mean how the the
the
fortuitous and I guess conspiracy
theorists are now losing their minds.
But to to be able to have two pilots who
were able there and get get this landed
absolutely fantastic and so glad
people's lives have been saved and I'll
save the false flag nonsense and and
whatever for a conspiracy show. uh
somebody else can handle that issue.
Chamath u listen it we we've said a lot
here about it. Uh glad everybody's safe.
Any final thoughts as we wrap?
>> A Omani national
stabbed an Indian pilot
and then tried to down a plane
full of Israelis. That is what happened.
And any attempt
to try to
cover up any of those facts is cowardly.
I've worked in Israel.
I've had some incredible memories there.
I think at some point we all just need
to take a step back and realize what
happened October 7th was horrible.
What's happened in Palestine also
horrible. But you cannot now see these
kinds of things and look past them
because you care more about a narrative
than what the facts are. Those were 150
earnest
normal people living lives.
>> Yeah.
>> Fathers, mothers, brothers, sisters,
kids. They didn't deserve to get plunged
into the ground and die.
So I think this idea that you can now
whitewash what happens enough is enough.
And I think we need to find a way to
actually tell the truth for what things
are.
So I was really really really
disappointed in how the media handled
it.
>> And I think it's and I think it's
dangerous. And I think um it's yet
another demonstration that these people
have absolutely no moral authority left
in society. They're just pathetic,
putrid,
>> and they're and by the way, they're
coordinated. When you see the words, the
same words over and over. Altercation,
altercation, altercation. It's very
powerful. It means that it starts from
one place.
>> And I think that, you know, if you
believe that you are reading this stuff
and you're getting the facts, you're
just not. And so,
>> well, it implies that one guy did
something wrong to the other guy and
they got in a fight. That's not what
happened. That's what it implies.
>> I I I'm trying to have the most
charitable interpretation here, like
>> why
>> to steal man it? So, in the moment, if
you didn't know what happened, but then,
you know, after it happened, you would
just very easily be able to say
potential terrorist.
>> There was footage coming from the
airplane,
>> of course. But how do you describe their
jail suicidal? That's that's my point.
In the moment, you could you could give
them a, hey, you don't know what's
happening. You want to be cautious here.
If it's a suicide, if it is an actual
fight or if it's a terrorist attack.
Okay, fine. I I could have a little bit
of room there to be like, okay, but then
after it, like, how could you not say
this is an apparent terrorist attack or
a mentally ill person? Those are the two
possibilities here. Period. Full stop.
And then you really have to get into
what what is the motivation here? Um,
yeah.
>> Look, I think the moral principle here
is that all attacks on civilians are
wrong. And that's what this was. And it
was, I mean, pretty clearly an act of
terrorism. And regardless of who's doing
it, that that's the the thing we have to
denounce is even when there's a military
conflict taking place, attacks on
civilians are wrong.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's a war crime.
>> And, you know, there's there's lot
there's a lot of that happening. So,
that's not the only case, but all of
that needs to stop.
>> All right. That's uh your all-in episode
291 for October 2nd, 2026. We'll see you
all next week. Bye-bye. Bye-bye.
>> Let your winners ride
>> it.
>> We open sourced it to the fans and
they've just gone crazy with it. Love
you.
>> Besties are gone.
>> This is my dog taking a notice in your
driveway.
>> Oh man, myasher will meet me at We
should all just get a room and just have
one big huge orgy cuz they're all just
useless. It's like this like sexual
tension that they just need to release
somehow.
Wet your feet.
>> We need to get merch. These are going
all in.
I'm going all in.